Guide to the John Moses photographs, 1974-1993 RL.11493
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Moses photographs
1974-1993
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Moses, John
RL.11493
1.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes 33 items
Collection of 23 photographs taken by John Moses, pediatrician and photographer, of teenaged parents and their children, chiefly in Durham, North Carolina and surrounding communities, and eight photographs of farmworkers taken in the South. Seeking to find the "human stories behind the statistics," he photographed the adolescent parents - almost all young women - in their homes and urban surroundings. A few images include grandparents. The photographs of farm laborers were taken in North Carolina, South Carolina, and Florida from 1974-1979, and include portraits of children, adults, and older people of all races at work and at home; also includes one of farmworkers protesting on a road as a bus with a Minute Maid sign rolls by. The gelatin silver prints all measure 11x14 inches. Includes an index of image titles and a three-page statement by Moses about his photography and its relevance to his medical work. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
31 prints and 2 typed manuscripts
Biographical / Historical
John Moses is a primary care pediatrician at Duke University Medical Center. While he was an undergraduate student at Duke, Moses took a photography class from CDS faculty member Alex Harris. Before attending medical school, he spent a year photographing the conditions of migrant farmworkers in the Southeast. He later photographed teenage parents in Durham, N.C. and surrounding communities. His current projects include a book about primary care medicine and a book about children and illness. His courses include Medicine and the Vision of Documentary Photography, part of the Focus Program, and Children and the Experience of Illness, in which students teach photography to children being treated for illness and write about their experiences during the semester. Moses plans to continue developing other opportunities for undergraduates to work with documentary studies and medicine.
[Source for some information: Center for Documentary Studies website, accessed June 21, 2017]
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The John Moses photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1993 and 2012.
Content Description
Collection of 23 photographs taken by John Moses, North Carolina pediatrician and photographer, of teenaged parents and their children, chiefly in Durham, North Carolina and surrounding communities, and eight photographs of farmworkers taken in the South.
Seeking to find the "human stories behind the statistics," Moses photographed the adolescent parents - almost all young women - in their homes and urban surroundings. A few images include grandparents. The photographs of farm laborers were taken in North Carolina, South Carolina, and Florida from 1974-1979, and include portraits of children, adults, and older people of all races at work and at home; also includes one of farmworkers protesting on a road as a bus with a Minute Maid sign rolls by.
The gelatin silver prints all measure 11x14 inches. Includes an index of image titles and a three-page statement by Moses about his photography and its relevance to his medical work. The description mentions oral histories conducted by Moses; these audio materials are not currently part of the collection.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Related Materials
The youngest parents: teenage pregnancy as it shapes lives, exhibit photographs, 1987-1996
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
The Youngest Parents: Teenage Pregnancy as it Shapes Lives, by Robert Cole. Durham, N.C.: Published by the Center for Documentary Studies; New York: In association with W.W. Norton, 1997
Duke University Libraries, Duke University
Agricultural laborers -- Southern States -- Portraits; Children of migrant laborers -- Portraits; Documentary Photography -- North Carolina; Documentary Photography -- Southern States; Migrant agricultural laborers -- Southern States -- Pictorial works; Teenage fathers -- North Carolina -- Durham; Teenage mothers -- North Carolina -- Durham; Teenage parents -- North Carolina -- Portraits; Teenagers -- Southern States -- Pictorial works; Durham (N.C.) -- Social conditions; North Carolina -- Social conditions; Southern States -- Social conditions; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- Teenage parents, 1986-1993; .5 Linear Feet 1 box 23 prints; 2 typewritten manuscripts 11x14 inches
  - Index to titles; artist's statement, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Sophia and William, Vance County, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Sharon and Cordavio, Vance County, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Janie and Rachel, Durham, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Granville County, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Ruth and Matthew, Mebane, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Ruth, Tracy, Marcus, and the triplets, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Pregnant teenager, Orange High School, Hillsborough, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Brenda and Bradley, Hillsborough, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Salechia and children, Orange County, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Tracy and sons, Mebane, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Theresa, her mother, and their children, Henderson, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Chris and Brandon, Henderson, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Sharon visiting, Alexandria, Virginia, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Brenda, sister Rhonda and Bradley, Hillsborough, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Vance County, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Chris and Brandon, Henderson, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Michelle and Chastity, Efland, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Henderson, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Orange County, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Orange County, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Twins with their babies and grandmother, Vance County, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Twins with their sons and grandfather, Vance County, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Cindy and Bradley, Orange County, 1989 (Box 1)
- Farmworkers, 1974-1979; .5 Linear Feet 1 box 8 prints 11x14 inches
  - No known title (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Young boy, arms crossed, standing in crop field.
  - No known title (Box 2)
    Young girl standing in fruit tree grove.
  - No known title (Box 2)
    Young boy standing in fruit tree grove.
  - No known title (Box 2)
    Group of agricultural workers waving flags by a roadside as a Minute Maid bus goes by.
  - No known title (Box 2)
    Workers sitting in front of decrepit housing.
  - No known title (Box 2)
    Elderly woman standing in front of stove, cooking a tortilla.
  - No known title (Box 2)
    Man standing in front of decrepit housing, holding liquor bottle.
  - No known title (Box 2)
    Man sitting on can in front of house.